<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Ramos on Software</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Ramos on Software</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.155.3</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 20:44:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Natural End of Software Development: Speaking English</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2026-02-06-the-natural-end-of-sw/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2026 20:44:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2026-02-06-the-natural-end-of-sw/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Natural End of Software Development: Speaking English&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately, my feed is full of panic about AI &amp;ldquo;replacing&amp;rdquo; software developers. The narrative is always the same: “If a machine can write the code, why do they need us?”
This fear stems from a misunderstanding of what we’ve actually been doing for the last 70 years. We weren&amp;rsquo;t hired to be &amp;ldquo;syntax experts&amp;rdquo;; we were hired to be translators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The History of Compression&lt;/strong&gt;
Software development has always been a game of reducing the friction between a human thought and a machine&amp;rsquo;s execution. We’ve just been climbing a ladder of abstraction:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ruminations on the post pandemic IT industry in Portugal</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2021-03-29-portuguese-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2021-03-29-portuguese-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the recent decades the business model for the IT industry in Portugal was mostly a nearshoring model, much of the industry profits from the difference between IT salaries in Portugal vs central Europe. Knowing that the average salary in Portugal is roughly 50% lower than Germany and it’s just 1h time difference, it’s easy to understand that this can be a very lucrative model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things start to change during the Portuguese debt crisis during the early 2010’s, due to the dim opportunities at home many Portuguese youngsters moved to other European countries – moving abroad was particularly easy for the “IT crowd” given that their skills were in high demand abroad and usually it’s not a job requirement to know any other language besides English.  This together with the fact that Portugal is a member of the EU and people can basically just decide to move other country and work there without much hassle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beware of people telling you how to build a MVP !</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2021-02-04-build-an-mvp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2021 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2021-02-04-build-an-mvp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;there-is-a-way-of-being-wrong-which-is-also-sometimes-necessarily-right---edward-abbey&#34;&gt;“There is a way of being wrong which is also sometimes necessarily right.” - Edward Abbey&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MVP stands for minimum viable product, and it is a popular thing between Agile software developers. A MVP  is a version of a product with just enough features to be usable by early customers who can then provide feedback for future product development. Software developers typically deploy the product to a subset of possible customers to get feedback and be able to grasp a proper product vision. Then with the collected feedback they improve the product and create a more evolved MVP, tough several interactions until they get to a kind of “final” release.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Docker in 6 minutes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-01-27-docker-in-6-minutes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2020 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2020-01-27-docker-in-6-minutes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;trying-to-make-some-sense--of-docker-for-non-technical-people&#34;&gt;Trying to make some sense  of docker for non-technical people.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you think it is more expensive to send a container full of goods from Lisbon to China or a plane ticket that allows one of you to go to from Lisbon to China? Actually it is roughly the same, the prices vary but on average the costs are around 1200 €.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is surprising that it is relatively cheap to transport such a huge container full of goods. More surprising to think that  despite all our innovations in transport, the item that really enabled globalization and allows to have todays supermarkets full of things from around the world at relatively low prices is a humble standard metal box more or less with 13mx3mx3m which allowed to lower transport costs in such a way that our supermarkets can full of products from all over the world at relatively low prices - to get an idea the cost of transport weighs on average less than 1% in the final cost of a product.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The subtle art of saying no</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-12-14-the-subtle-art-of-saying-no---copy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-12-14-the-subtle-art-of-saying-no---copy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been wondering a lot about the importance of saying no recently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally I’ve been trying to focus on important things and say no to other stuff that ends up consuming a lot of energy but is not that relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professionally as a Product Owner I got to say no a lot ! actually I think the art to say no is one of the most important characteristics of a good PO.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In the end it&#39;s all about the people</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-11-30-its-all-about-the-people---copy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2019 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-11-30-its-all-about-the-people---copy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I really like this article I’ve read in Increment [The epistemology of software quality] ( &lt;a href=&#34;https://increment.com/teams/the-epistemology-of-software-quality/&#34;&gt;https://increment.com/teams/the-epistemology-of-software-quality/&lt;/a&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Say you run a new team. You have carte blanche to implement any policies you want to make the team more productive and the code less buggy. What do you do? You could choose a new programming language, or switch everything to microservices, or follow the hottest trend in process. Or you could do things that matter. You could pace schedules. You could ensure that no one works more than eight hours a day. You could let people off 20 minutes early to avoid rush hour. You could make it as easy as possible for parents to take the day off when their kids are sick. You could make people feel like they’re important, because people are important. No method, tool, or language matters nearly as much as our own minds.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Telco ML</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-09-06-telco-ml-p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2019 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-09-06-telco-ml-p1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While having some training on machine learning, I’ve been thinking in how it could be applied to telco software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a huge array of equipment necessary to enable you to use your mobile phone with minimal issues, your operator has lots of radio equipment spread around that enables your phone to communicate with the network and a core network that enables the data to travel around ( this is of course a huge simplification ).
Lot’s of equipment spread in larger areas means of course lot’s of problems, there are the obvious equipment malfunctions, there are power breakdowns and even more “unexpected” events like someone stealing a network antenna.
Telco operators employ lot’s of people and use sophisticated software to ensure that their systems are functional, this is a growing challenge as more and more equipment is necessary to support newer network standards like 5G.
Several functions of the Telco OSS systems, [ OSS meaning Operations Support System ] ( &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operations_support_system&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operations_support_system&lt;/a&gt; ) not Open Source Software, involve something like :&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous Everything</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-08-27-continuous-everything/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2019 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-08-27-continuous-everything/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve found out this week that the famous &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2000/08/09/the-joel-test-12-steps-to-better-code/&#34;&gt;Joel test&lt;/a&gt; reached 19 years of age this month, besides reminding me how old I’m getting  it reminded me of the importance of proper CI/CD - [Continuous Integration] (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_integration&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_integration&lt;/a&gt;) / [Continuous Delivery] (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_delivery&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_delivery&lt;/a&gt;) pipelines in software development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time I’ve came across “Joel Test”, found that comply with rule number 2 migth be a good thing and I’ve tried to create a simple build script that would emulate a kind of basic CI pipe – at the time I was working on a application composed of a set of components based on Win32 DLL’s+EXE; my CI script would compile the necessary DLL’s, join them in a directory and check if it run. Seems and it’s quite basic but it was really helpful, you would be surprised by how many times things got messed up, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dependency_hell&#34;&gt;Dependency_hell&lt;/a&gt; Someone ? , I was convinced how valuable was this early feedback tool, thus have been a fan of CI/CD for the rest and most part of my professional live.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ruminations about programming languages </title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-04-12-ruminations_about_programming_languages/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2019 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-04-12-ruminations_about_programming_languages/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I’ve come across a post in Quora about the “end of Java”, kind of funny these doomsday predictions regarding programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve starting to learn programming somewhere around the late 80’s when I was a kid, at the time I’ve learn basic … it was the most common language for kids who owned “PC’s” with 48k of memory. Basic programs tended to be quite difficult to read and one thing that you learn from experience ( sometimes the hard way ) is that it is generally much difficult to maintain and evolve computer software than to initially write it, thus putting effort in to make it clean and adaptable pays off.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dependency Hell v2019 </title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-02-04-dependency-hell-v2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-02-04-dependency-hell-v2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A recent problem that one of the teams I work with faced, related to a major DB vendor and a set of different incompatible patches remind me of the 90’s. During the late 90’s I’ve worked for a Windows shop that developed a huge DLL based application, taking care of dependencies was a nightmare…early MS win 95 versions didn’t include any good mechanism to track DLL versions, also initially this was not a major concern when developing our application, but we end up creating a lot of DLLs and with additional dependencies from SO and 3rd party DLL’s, so I know fist hand what “DLL hell” means. By the way the term “dependency hell “ is a common software problem that has the honor of it’s own &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dependency_hell&#34;&gt;Wikipedia entry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More About Helm - Tips</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-01-21-more-about-helm-tips/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2019 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-01-21-more-about-helm-tips/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Helm is one of the best tools available to simplify your kubernetes development. In this post I’ll be adding some tips that might help you in the development of your helm charts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Btw, you migth like to see &lt;a href=&#34;../2018-12-19-about-helm/&#34;&gt;this previous post&lt;/a&gt; and eventually [this one] (../2019-01-04-more-about-helm-values/)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tip-1--files-in-configmaps&#34;&gt;Tip 1 – Files in configmaps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are cases where you will need to move existing configuration files to config maps, a hard working solution is to just type in the whole file with the proper config map indentation.
A more practical solution is to use helm .Files.Glob command. This command will map the content of files in a specific directory to your config map.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The logging triology - ELK Elasticsearch &#43; Logstash &#43; Kibana</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-01-08-the-log-triollogy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2019 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-01-08-the-log-triollogy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the side effects of a microservices architecture is that checking logs soon becomes a problem. At the beginning of the process, when you think about containerizing an application, it seems simple and straightforward – you just log to stdout and docker or kubernetes handle it. But then &amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-is-my-log-&#34;&gt;Where is my log ?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of different services &amp;amp; service instances rapidly explodes and then it becomes really difficult to find a particular log and to troubleshoot the misbehaviour of a micro-service. The solution is to add a log management application, something to store your logs and to allow you to search through them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More About Helm - Values</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-01-04-more-about-helm-values/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2019 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2019-01-04-more-about-helm-values/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Manage deployments is a import concern when creating a microservices based application, given the typical huge number of services involved and the possible variations you need a way to keep complexity under control.
Helm can be a usefull tool, besides been a very cool way to define dependencies ( &lt;a href=&#34;../2018-12-19-about-helm/&#34;&gt;see this previous post&lt;/a&gt; ),  Helm introduces an interesting concept called values ( not quite original, but implemented in a nice way ). Values allows you to redefine parts your kubernetes yaml (*) files on deployment time, thus allowing more flexibility to your application and, if done right, simplify the deployment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My favorite BuzzWords for 2018</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-12-21-favorite-buzzwords/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Dec 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-12-21-favorite-buzzwords/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Techies love BuzzWords, every year there is new popular technology or concept that everyone talks about,  soon these fall in to oblivion and are replaced by new trends. Not all the Buzzwords referrer to completely useless stuff, some concepts really got past the Buzz part and became really useful parts of our lives, but eventually people got tired to discuss them, or they became too common to be interesting ( I guess Blog was a buzzword a few years ago ).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About Helm</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-12-19-about-helm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-12-19-about-helm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Microservices are supposed to be small and dedicated, the issue when you move an application to a microservices based architecture is that you quickly get many of them. Dealing with each service individually becomes much easier as they get more “micro”, but deal with the whole bunch can be a nightmare.
Look at the example bellow, in the 1st interaction of a typical application it became something like this :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;+-------------------------+        +-------------------------+
|     typical-frontend    |        |      typical-backend    |
|                         |        |                         |
+-------------------------+        +-------------------------+
                                                              
+-------------------------+        +-------------------------+
|     typical-database    |        |      typical-interf     |
|                         |        |                         |
+-------------------------+        +-------------------------+
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;But then developers became more familiar with microservices, start splitting them in more specialized tasks and it became this :&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Telco Software : Virtualization vs Cloudification</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-12-18-telco-software--virtualization-vs-cloudification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-12-18-telco-software--virtualization-vs-cloudification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I came across this very interesting article on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.economist.com/business/2017/04/12/cloudification-will-mean-upheaval-in-telecoms&#34;&gt;The Economist&lt;/a&gt; regarding “Cloudification will mean upheaval in telecoms”, it’s kind of “old news” but make me think about the current trends in telco software development.
From my experience telco industry was fast to virtualize but slot to cloudify. Virtualization and cloudification are often used with the same meaning but they are actually different concepts. Virtualization is mostly related to the optimization of hardware resources, running more software on a given amount of physical infrastructure. Cloud computing is  a metaphor for a system that is based on a shared pool of configurable computer resources that can be provisioned over the internet, typically with minimal effort - public cloud services like Amazon AWS are highly automated, elastic/scalable and pay-as-you-go ( you just need a credit card ). Cloud computing makes use of virtualization to enable the elasticity and achieve economies of scale.
For many years telco operators have been using virtualized solutions at the core of their networks, virtualization is expanding to more and network functions, in particular at the edge of the network.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About not-so-microservices</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-12-17-not-so-microservices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-12-17-not-so-microservices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, in particular when moving large legacy systems to a microservices architecture you came up with the dilemma, what to do about the not-so-microservices ? these are typically large monolith blocks from a bygone era. Developers are afraid of these, no one want’s to mess with them. But we live in a messy world with lot’s of IT infrastructure relying on old code – it is not possible to rewrite all the old code in a “container friendly” way.
Thus what to do when you have to deal with a large service, that doesn’t seem to fit well on a microservices architecture ?
My view is that, generally the best option is to containerize it anyway – likely you will end up with a very large container, but docker architecture and existing tools are flexible enough to handle most common challenges.
In the end you’ll end up with a far from ideal system, but at least it will be a system where all the services are managed in a consistent way. The alternative, to have a part of the system outside the Kubernetes containerized platform is likely much worse in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Ingress triology</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-12-14-expose-kubernertes-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-12-14-expose-kubernertes-services/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Deploying http services in a Kubernetes cluster can be a bit challenging, although the basic principles are simple it is not always easy to manage all the details.  Docker &amp;amp; Kubernetes were designed with isolation in mind  ( they are called containers for a reason ).
You need to understand the Ingress triology properlly :
Ingress -&amp;gt; Service -&amp;gt; Containers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-container&#34;&gt;The Container&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fist step is to have the container running, inside the container there is a service running that accepts HTTP connections – let’s say tomcat running a webserver.
The tricky part is that it is not enough to have the service running inside the container.
Imagine that you ssh to the container and check the service, lile&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Developing Secure Applications</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-11-19-develop-secure-appls/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-11-19-develop-secure-appls/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Everyday there is a new story about a hacking incident somewhere, developing secure applications is definitely one of the most important challenges in the software world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good analogy is the defence of a castle, in the medieval world castles were very important. In a anarchic world with many threads  they were the centres of power and stability. But how to defend a castle from your enemy’s ? a well built castle in a high point was a clear advantage, will a relatively small force it could be defended against a much powerful enemy.
But as a defended you had to make sure that you didn’t miss any spot, the enemy would look for weak points and you would have to make sure that you had none. Defences must be built and then continuously maintained and updated.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>what goes online stays online ? yes 22 years latter</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-11-01-22-years-online/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-11-01-22-years-online/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thinking about the differences between life now and “before the internet” remind me that many years ago, just a bit after I’ve started to use the internet I’ve created a web site…is is true that &amp;ldquo;what goes online stays online&amp;rdquo; ?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, defenitly during the late 90&amp;rsquo;s I’ve used [Geocities] (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yahoo!_GeoCities&#34;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yahoo!_GeoCities&lt;/a&gt;) , a free hosting service at the time that eventually was bought by Yahoo.
To have an online presence during the web early days mean that you would have to hack your own html static pages, get a crappy background and deploy it on Geocities. The portal was organized in a “neighbourhood” fashion, depending on the theme of your site you would pick the appropriate neighbourhood – at the time I was still a student and quite interested in game development, thus my site was about C++ game development using Microsoft Direct X that was kind of a new technology at the time.
Geocities was closed in 2009, but I could find my “old” site in the [web achieve] (&lt;a href=&#34;https://web.archive.org/web/20000816161746/http://www.geocities.com/SiliconValley/Heights/3098/&#34;&gt;https://web.archive.org/web/20000816161746/http://www.geocities.com/SiliconValley/Heights/3098/&lt;/a&gt; )&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Read last week</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-10-12-read-last-week-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-10-12-read-last-week-3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>E-Nightmare</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-08-24-e-nightmare/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Aug 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-08-24-e-nightmare/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;“E-Government” has been quite a trendy buzzword all around Europe, according to the UN E-Government survey Portugal &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;ranks 29 in worldwide E-Government services&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; which is not great but not too bad either. For sake of comparison number 1 is Denmark, Belgium is 28 and Poland 33.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway It is cool that many public services have been made available online. I just wonder what the ranking would be if they considered security. It is relatively simple to push public services online,  but if these are not properly secured this can create more serious problems than the ones it solves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The new normal ?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-08-17-165/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-08-17-165/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, CUF hospital, one of the biggest Portuguese private hospitals was attacked by ransomware, &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;you can read about it here if you can read Portuguese&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;seems that the  the SamSam ransomware was used, likely by the same grupo that &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;has been targeting hospitals around the globe&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are not many details available, the Hospital claims that “Everything is normal”, but apparently  some exams were lost, likely encrypted by the ransomware, as they refused to pay for the ransom. In particular it is not known how the hackers were able to get in to the system.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Read last week - Whois GDPR ?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-04-30-read-last-week-whois-gdpr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-04-30-read-last-week-whois-gdpr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Read Last Week - Everybody loves Facebook !</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-26-read-last-week-everybody-loves-facebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-26-read-last-week-everybody-loves-facebook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DST and Software</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-26-dst-and-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-26-dst-and-software/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last weekend was a 47 hour oddity; across Europe it is like this every last weekend of March due to the annual DST change to “Summer Hour”. It is annoying but I know if could be worse, at least these changes are unified and regulated, thus all the counties that are part of the EU &amp;ldquo;unified clock regime&amp;rdquo; make the change in the same day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These changes tend to remind me of years ago when I’ve worked in a software that processed Television audiences, what to do with the GAP when the clock jumps from SAT 1:00 AM to SAT 2:00 AM ? in our case we have decided to “duplicate” the 0:00 to 1:00 period, but a dedicated routine was written in C++ to handle it. Not actually an easy task…jumping time doesn’t make life easy for software developers, in particular if the software somehow relates to continuous time related data.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Read last week - Cambridge Analytica</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-20-read-last-week-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-20-read-last-week-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;BBC on Cambridge Analytica&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tech giant Facebook and data analytics firm Cambridge Analytica are at the centre of a dispute over the harvesting and use of personal dat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;BGR on Slingshot&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nation-state developed a piece of malware so powerful that it can steal everything that’s happening on a computer without even being install on the target device itself. Instead, it resides on a router. It’s called Slingshot and it was recently discovered by Kaspersky Labs. Incredibly, the malware is so powerful and sophisticated that it hid in routers for six years before finally being spotted&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Read last week - MoviePass</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-12-read-last-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-12-read-last-week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Wow&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MoviePass CEO Mitch Lowe told an audience at a Hollywood event last Friday that the app &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;tracks moviegoers&amp;rsquo; locations before and after each show they watch&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;. &amp;ldquo;We get an enormous amount of information,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Hardcoded Password Found in Cisco Software&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How do I know if a particular Web site is secure ? HTTP vs HTTPs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-09-how-do-i-know-if-a-particular-web-site-is-secure-part-1-http-vs-https/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-09-how-do-i-know-if-a-particular-web-site-is-secure-part-1-http-vs-https/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;The short answer is you don’t know … there is no simple ways to check, web infrastructure these days is complex and there is no public reporting of security practices used or even testing reports. The web owner can ( and will if they care about security ) use some kind of vulnerability testing, but it’s actually not nice to test 3rd party sites for vulnerabilities and generally people don’t make these public.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is P@ssword1 more secure than password ?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-06-is-pssword1-more-secure-than-password/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-06-is-pssword1-more-secure-than-password/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On the scope on the GDPR there was some recent news in Portugal regarding Government guidelines for online public services. Atually public service security is an important issue as in Portugal we have lot’s of personal info in public sites, for example a service call eFactura stores basically every invoice where you have put a VAT number – thus very valuable info.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new guidelines are still under discussion, but a kind of pre-release showed up today in todays specialized press. Some of the measurements are basic security common sense like “Usage of plain text credentials in code or configuration files is forbidden” or  “there should be a access control policy defined”. Others are a bit odd like “Passwords should have a minimum length of 9 characters using lower and uppercase, numbers and special characters”.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Read last week</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-05-read-last-wekk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-05-read-last-wekk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;The economist on “self driving cars” &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particularly interesting is this part regarding privacy “&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;AVs will record everything that happens in and around them. When a crime is committed, the police will ask nearby cars if they saw anything. Fleet operators will know a great deal about their riders&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Privacy vs Value</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-01-75/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-03-01-75/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Data is new Oil, I don’t know who came up with the analogy, I think I’ve read it 1st &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;on Wired&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;but it really highlight’s the value of data these days.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;This should be a reminder that data is valuable, likely you wouldn’t consider sending a few bottles of gasoline to BP just because it’s fun but you produce a huge amount of data that you are giving to online companies without getting much in return. &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About Bitcoin, Cryptocurrencies and Cryptomining</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-02-27-about-bitcoin-cryptocurrencies-and-cryptomining/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-02-27-about-bitcoin-cryptocurrencies-and-cryptomining/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;The current cryptocurrency trend brings fresh challenges to security, and should be a concern even if you, like me don’t understand where’s the fun of Bitcoin and don’t care much about it.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Cryptocurrencies were one of the greatest trends in 2017, in particular the crypto “star” Bitcoin that started the year around 1000$ and ended it well above 10000$. Although I really don’t find Bitcoin particularly interesting ( just go elsewhere if you are looking for investment tips – I’m not really good at it ) I think that the concept behind it, Blockchain, has potential and can be useful in a lot of different ways.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About Spectre &amp; Meltdown</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-02-23-about-spectre-meltdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-02-23-about-spectre-meltdown/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;For several reasons Meltdown and Spectre are a very interesting set of vulnerabilities that illustrates well the challenges involved to create secure software applications these days.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Details &amp;amp; more info in :&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://meltdownattack.com/&#34;&gt;https://meltdownattack.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Some semi random thoughts about it : &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About GDPR</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-02-23-about-gdpr/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-02-23-about-gdpr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;GDPR is something that is been given some headaches to people like me, involved in secure software development, it stands for “General Data Protection Regulation” ( see&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eugdpr.org/&#34;&gt;https://www.eugdpr.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; ), it’s a new EU wide regulation coming from the  European Parliament that impacts  companies that collect or process data related to European Citizens. The GDPR will be enforced after 25 May 2018 and means potential heavy fines for non-complaint companies.&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
