<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Virtualization on Ramos on Software</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/virtualization/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Virtualization on Ramos on Software</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.155.3</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2018 13:23:10 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/virtualization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Telco Software : Virtualization vs Cloudification</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-12-18-telco-software--virtualization-vs-cloudification/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2018 13:23:10 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/posts/2018-12-18-telco-software--virtualization-vs-cloudification/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I came across this very interesting article on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.economist.com/business/2017/04/12/cloudification-will-mean-upheaval-in-telecoms&#34;&gt;The Economist&lt;/a&gt; regarding “Cloudification will mean upheaval in telecoms”, it’s kind of “old news” but make me think about the current trends in telco software development.
From my experience telco industry was fast to virtualize but slot to cloudify. Virtualization and cloudification are often used with the same meaning but they are actually different concepts. Virtualization is mostly related to the optimization of hardware resources, running more software on a given amount of physical infrastructure. Cloud computing is  a metaphor for a system that is based on a shared pool of configurable computer resources that can be provisioned over the internet, typically with minimal effort - public cloud services like Amazon AWS are highly automated, elastic/scalable and pay-as-you-go ( you just need a credit card ). Cloud computing makes use of virtualization to enable the elasticity and achieve economies of scale.
For many years telco operators have been using virtualized solutions at the core of their networks, virtualization is expanding to more and network functions, in particular at the edge of the network.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
